[Music]
Welcome to this Business Central launch
event about what's new in Algo Go for
GitHub on built and performance. My name
is Freddy Christensen, technical
evangelist with Microsoft and together
with me I have Alexander. I work with
Freddy on Algo Go for GitHub and I'm
part of the engineering systems team at
Microsoft.
So in algo go for GitHub um in this
release we have quite a few things like
on build and performance. So and and
we'll like go through these not in
detail but just like on the surface and
try to explain to you what what these
things uh are good for and and how they
can help you in your DevOps solution.
The first was one is incremental builds
and let's have a look at what that
actually is. So incremental builds is
all about only building what's needed.
So if you're modifying if you have like
a repository with 10 apps or 10
projects, you'll only build the apps
that are actually modified in the commit
that you uh you're running right now. Um
default like if we go back in time, this
has always been enabled for pull
requests, but it has never been enabled
for for a CI/CD. The primary reason for
that was that we wanted every CI/CD
build to have like a complete set of
artifacts built and we've solved that.
So we're saving time on continuous
integration when only building what's
needed, but we're also saving time on
deploying because the unbuilt apps will
obviously not be deployed. They'll like
figure out that these apps are already
deployed.
Let's have a quick demo of what this
actually contains. If we have a look at
the build here, like there's a lot of uh
different uh commits here, but I'll just
have a look at at this commit and click
this one and have a look at this build.
Total duration 24 minutes. Looking at
the first build here, these builds are
like 24 seconds. Obviously, that's not a
complete build. Uh but here we have like
normal build time for when doing like uh
a normal build using GitHub uh runners
is approximately 15 minutes per app. So
what's happening here is that the only
apps here that have been rebuilt is the
Danish one and the Italian one uh and
actually with different build modes as
well. Um but looking at that uh the
artifacts for the build is complete.
We'll both have the common we'll have
the Italian one. We'll have Danish one.
We'll have the W1 app. Uh so so all the
artifacts are there. But if we look at
what's inside these artifacts, the W1
one will actually
be the artifacts from the previous
build and the Danish one will be the
artifact from this build. Looking at the
summary, we'll be able to see
that the artifacts that are not built is
taken from the last known good build,
which is this one should then be build
number 22 somewhere, I guess. Whatever.
Yeah, build number 22 up here. So, the
artifacts that were not built is copied
from the last known good build, meaning
that the build that we are uh using and
running with will be uh complete. Back
to the
presentation. Let's have a look at the
next thing which also kind of works
together with incremental builds quite a
bit. Uh workflow concurrency. Now um
what you can do with workflow
concurrency is to control workflow
concurrency. Wow. Kind of like says
itself. Um it works very well with
incremental builds. If you set up
incremental builds on a branch or on a
uh on a repository, then the workflow
concurrency can ensure that if if you
are doing like two commits after each
other, it's going to cancel the prior
build and just build the the next one.
And because of incremental builds will
look at the last known good build and
the changes since the last known good
build. It will it will find all the
changes between uh the last known good
build and what we're building right now.
Let's have a look at that. The last
known good build we had was build number
22. That's this one. After that, we did
a commit here which was cancelled. And
the reason for that was obviously that
we did another commit like seconds later
uh which is 24. Let's look at what
actually was changed in 23. What we did
here was we we made a change to the
Italian version. If we then go back and
have a look at the change we did in the
24 that was one change in the Danish
version. And as we saw earlier, the
built made in 24 here actually uh builds
both the Italian one and the Danish one
because both of those changed since the
last known good build. Uh so this way
having workflow concurrency set together
with incremental build uh will will save
you quite a bit of time. Let's look at
the settings just to see what actually
is necessary in Elgo settings here and
the let me see here the conditional
settings here for workflow concurrency
is here and the incremental builds are
set here to run on push and on pull
requests but not on
schedule with that let's go back to the
presentation and I'll give the word to
Alexander to talk about conditional
setting based
build modes.
So, taking a step back first, let's just
talk about what build modes are. Uh, so
in this settings file here, you can see
I have I've defined a default build mode
and a next major build mode. This
basically allows me to build uh the
project in two different configurations,
default and next major. But algo doesn't
really out of the box do much different
for these two build modes. So, in the
past, what you've been able to do is you
could add a script override. For
example, you could say if default mode
then do this, if next major mode then do
that. Uh but with the latest version of
Ego now, we also support conditional
settings based on build modes.
So when you build your CI/CD, you'll get
these build common uh in default and
next major mode. And now with
conditional settings, you can then
specify that in your next major build
mode, for example, it might make sense
that you want to grab the next major
artifact rather than the 25.4 artifact.
And so ALGO will grab the conditional
setting here when we're building in next
major mode and we'll grab the next major
artifact instead of the 25.4 artifact.
Next up is pre-processor symbols. So
again, AL lets you add these
prep-processor symbols to your code.
Like in this case, we can add this
global tag to our code. And that means
when we build this app, when we specify
the global uh prep-processor direct
directive, then we'll include this code
otherwise we won't. And uh now you'll go
also supports adding prep-processor
symbols as a setting. So you can add
this prep-processor symbol setting which
is an array and then you just give
however many of these uh prep-processor
symbols that you're using in your code.
So in this case we're telling our ALGO
project please build using this global
symbol. Um so when we pass when we
compile the app we pass this global
symbol to the compiler and then it gets
it gets used. If we go back to the
previous example around conditional
settings you can also apply
pre-processor symbols in in this
situation as well. So you could imagine
that your AL project uh has some
different logic based on whether you're
building the default version or on the
next major version. And so in your
conditional settings, you can just add
the prep-processor symbols that you
need. So in this case, just add the next
major prep-processor symbol if that's
what you're using. And algo will build
using the next major prep-processor
symbols in the next major build mode.
And in the default mode it won't use u
this these preprocessor symbols.
So next topic is no more this built
artifacts. Um
so in the old days or up until until
this version
um you would see artifacts like this
where you had like a project the apps
and and build output and maybe test app
test result and stuff like that. And
then you'd have like this build and then
a project name and then apps or this
build and then a project name and then
test
apps. They were used for um for building
multi- project builds where one project
had dependencies on the other project.
So we kind of had to create an artifact
uh an artificial artifact that the other
project could use and and the the
retention uh period for that one was one
day. Now in this new version we actually
create full artifacts in all builds. Um
we do create them as shortlived
artifacts meaning that you can you can
use a setting to to define that that
these shortlived artifacts can be more
than a day. Right now they are uh one
day um but we are just using these
normal artifacts for the uh resulting um
for the for the project that we're
building afterwards. Now it's hard to
demo that something is gone. So I don't
have a demo on this, but if you if you
like stumble over that normally you had
these artifacts, you don't have them
anymore. That is because we now always
create full artifacts that are
short-lived and you can create a setting
for
that. There's a new versioning strategy
in the latest version of algo versioning
strategy 3. Um we had some partners like
talk
about why is only major minor defined by
appjson when you demand like a a release
to have three digits. Well, it actually
makes sense to have a versioning
strategy where three digits are
controlled by appjon and only one digit
controlled by GitHub which is the fourth
digit. So using versioning strategy 3
you will have major minor and built
controlled by appjon and then when you
release you will know exactly this is
the version that I want to release and
you can specify that in your release and
and the fourth digit will be the the
counter uh to to run that with that um
over to Alexander. Yes and the final
topic for this session here is commit
options. Uh so again taking a step back
certain algo workflows can create pull
requests or do direct commits into your
repository. Uh example of such could be
update algo system files or increment
version number. And a piece of feedback
that we got from partners was that you
want to be able to inject some kind of
message into the commit message or into
the pull request. And so in the latest
versions of go we now allow that. Uh so
what you'll do is you'll add this commit
options construct. And within here you
have three options. You can specify a
message suffix. So this gets added to
the end of your commit message or at the
end of your pull
request. If you are creating pull
requests then you can also specify if
they should be
automerged. Uh and finally we allow
adding pull request
labels. Uh so with that let me go into a
demo. So we're here in the Microsoft BC
apps repository. This is where the
system application and the business
foundation lives. And in here we use
algo and we're also using commit
options. So if we go into the github
folder and under algo settings scroll
all the way down you can see we're using
this commit options construct. Now the
reason we use this related to ab hashtag
and then an ID is because we use the
Azure boards integration. This is an app
that we've installed in our repository
where when you specify AB hashtag and a
number then we link we link that pull
request to a work item in Azure DevOps.
This is how we kind of get a better
integration between GitHub and Ashure
DevOps. Uh and similar kinds of
integrations exist for other work item
management tools. So with this with
these commit options set if we go to an
example of a pull
request. So this was last time we
updated Elgo system files. As you can
see we're updating system files. Here
you get all the release notes and then
as specified we get this automation
labeled
applied. We scroll all the way
down we get this related to suffix that
has a link to uh Ashure DevOps. So if
you click here it'll take you to our
Azure DevOps project. We can see the
work item and so on. Uh and finally it
sets the automatic automerge option
automatically. So all I have to do as a
maintainer is just to look through the
files, look through the release notes
and then approve and then it gets merged
into a repository. So with that, thanks
for watching the video. Thank you.